I assume that you are new to streaming
and for some reason you heard or
read somewhere that you need exactly this,
this program you want to
use. Perhaps you want to
conduct game streams, maybe you
need to record a course, some kind of webinar, a
presentation, just something, show it on the
screen with your comments, make a
video out of it, send it to someone.
We will talk about all this now for
beginners and you will understand that it is not
scary, that it is all quickly possible to
understand without stuffiness and then If you want to
somehow get into the wilds about this,
I already have other videos. I think
downloading the OBS program was not a
big problem for you, but just in case, I
will leave a link in the description and most likely,
when you first launch it, you will see this
window of the automatic
configuration wizard if suddenly you closed it and
want to show it again, this is the
service item of the automatic configuration wizard
when it was first introduced in OBS,
this automatic configuration wizard,
which was intended to help beginners, it
configured complete nonsense, but now, in general, it
can really be used. I
tested it, it's cool and At this
stage, especially  If you are a beginner and
don't understand anything about this program at all, you
can really use
the tips of this automatic
setup wizard. If you want to broadcast
something live, select the first
item. If you want to record something for
future editing. Perhaps, or
you will simply transfer it as a video file to
someone or upload it somewhere. Select this.
In fact, it won't really matter here
what you choose. You won't
break anything. These are just the initial
settings designed to help
beginners figure it out and start doing
something. Let's move on and most likely,
you won't need to change anything here. The
base resolution will be set
automatically to the size of
your desktop resolution and the resolution of
your main monitor. It's correctly
written in the note. If anything, don't worry.
You can then broadcast or record in different
resolutions, but more on that later.
Frame purity. Insert 60. If you
are going to stream games, especially
first-person shooters, there the
smoothness of the image. 50 frames per second
looks very advantageous. If you
are recording some presentations or
tables.  Broadcast or
collect and record, then
30 FPS will be enough for you. You don't need this smoothness
and
you don't need extra load on the hardware for the encoder. Let's move on and
since we chose at the beginning that we are primarily a
Streamer. Yes, we are going to
broadcast something live, our
creativity, games, or anything. We strive
with the help of OBS, you can do anything, any
kind of creativity, any kind of
content. Here you can choose the
platform on which you are going to
stream: Twitch, YouTube, and so on. These will
most likely be the most popular
choices. If it is possible to connect
an account, then this is recommended as written in brackets, it
will be more convenient, you will not
need to worry about
broadcast keys. But if you suddenly stream to
some sites that are not very popular, some
niche ones, and so on, but which
provide the ability to
send a stream there and stream there, maybe
some courses. Yes, individual sites,
then most likely this site will provide
you with a stream key, it will look like a
long set of characters, no big
deal, so you can stream anywhere.
Even to everything on Twitch, YouTube, and so
on, to anything, you just need to
go to the site in  In the settings there are
broadcasts get this stream key
now I am authorized with my account
on Twitch And you authorized with any
other account Where are you going to
stream YouTube There Facebook and so on
there is a huge list of
platforms If you click next Then a
bandwidth test will be carried out, that
is, a test of your Internet server will be selected
But if you still have not chosen
where you will be you will stream and you
want to master this program or you are
not interested in streaming at all, you
are going to just record
video here, then at the first stage If you
choose to optimize only for
recording I will not broadcast then
this item will not be here at all the
same and that's it click here apply
settings and click in the lower right corner of the
settings but for now don't be scared by this
number of different settings
when audio and so on and so on
just in general put these
checkboxes show who confirms when
starting a broadcast show broadcast
permutations the same for
recording I think you understand that there is
nothing worse than when you
unplanned go on air just
accidentally button  pressed And there
the broadcast has already started or the recording has been stopped
or the Stream has been stopped accidentally, you didn’t
mean to do this, a confirmation will be
displayed there, these checkboxes
will save you from a bunch of errors. So, I
said that the stuffiness is ending, so
we press OK, don’t worry about other
settings and finally get acquainted with the
program interface, this
black square is black for now, this is just the
canvas, the very resolution that
we chose in the
Automatic Settings Wizard, think of it
as a landscape sheet on which you
will draw everything that will appear in the future.
Here in this black square or
instead of this black square, you
can record or broadcast to the
Internet and this will be a live
streaming broadcast of some kind of
movement happening with you. Well,
actually, start creating and
somehow fill in this Malevich rectangle, here
in the sources, we begin
to add any pictures here, maybe
you need to capture the screen,
click on this plus sign or right-
click on this source zone
to add and here, accordingly, the
list. What can you do?  Add
guys, I'm from the future for a minute, I'll
tell you at the ditch that if you suddenly don't
want to deal with this yourself, you
need to quickly set something up specifically for your task,
look at the settings, then I have
paid consultations at the link in the
description, you'll find a Google document
with all the information, depending on
when you view it,
something can be added there, there are just ideas on how to
implement some services. A little later, I'll do all this, I'll figure it out,
organize it, but
naturally, I don't want to be the person that
every schoolchild can call
there for 200 rubles so that I can set up their BS.
I'm specifically talking about people who
value their time and want to speed things up
and maybe even want to implement something
based on OBS, or some kind of podcast with
several people. Yes, with NES, with a microphone,
and so on, OBS is a fairly
professional program. All this can be
implemented, you can implement it with a human
director. There is a
studio mode, a very powerful theme, you can really cut a
huge amount of content and
record, stream online, and so
on. If anything, write. We'll think about it, figure it out, decide,
see what can be
done. But we're returning to the video,
learning.  Let's discuss from scratch. In 99 percent of
cases, the basis of your content will most likely
be something happening on the
computer screen. This could be a game,
it could be a window of some application
you are working in. Or it will be a
screen capture. As for game capture,
everything is clear: you launch some game,
add game capture, call it
something. This is only for your convenience.
If anything, so that you understand what it is,
click OK and most likely, you wo
n't need to do anything here, the
game will be picked up automatically. The
only thing I immediately recommend is one
of these more advanced things.
But you can watch this in other videos. If
anything, limit the capture frequency, click and that's it,
click OK. Well, I completely forgot about
those who play on Steam and perhaps you
want your
achievements received and so on to be visible on the screen. Then click on
the capture of these third-party overlays. This is what we are
talking about and click OK now.
So far, nothing has appeared because
we have not captured any game. We
can delete everything with the Delete button or with the trash
bin, select what we
need. Click the Delete button. Now let's
consider window capture and screen capture.  I
think it is clear that this is necessary for those who
want to show how he works in
some application,
fills out some tables. Perhaps, and so on, any kind of
engine can be on the
screen. And you need to convey it somehow. As
for window capture, this is convenient
when you need to separately show the window of some
application and not
show the rest, then you can use the alt tab
to switch to other windows, maybe
reply to someone's private messages, and
so on, but the audience will see only
this window. Click on window capture. Call
it something like a
notepad window, because in this example I
will show the name. Only for you
for your convenience. Okay, and now we see
that the notepad window is being captured. It is
selected here, naturally, we can
select any window of your browser or
your other
software. Any window works. In this
case, it is a notepad. We don’t
touch everything else. Just click OK. We
got a window in the resolution in which
you have it open. If you expand it
to full screen, then here it will
also stretch accordingly. It is very
important to understand that in this case, when
you capture a window, you can
position it however you like. If
you make changes to it,  For
example, let's say I need to make something like this, well,
such an artistic solution. I
start my work and you see that
here,
too, everything changes. You can specifically
work in this window,
show something, and on the broadcast, everything will be as
you arranged it, let's say, for you. But it is
necessary that this is how it was exactly
here. Most likely, for someone,
this will still be inconvenient. You need to
show the entire screen so as not to worry, not to
bring up different windows, not to fly back
to the OS and not to switch between these
windows. Using screen capture in
this case is very convenient. You also
create a screen capture. Delete the
previous unnecessary source. It's better
to get used to it so as not to create garbage and
then not get confused in the
sources. We add a screen capture. If
you have one monitor, you
don't need to do anything else here, you will immediately see the picture,
but if you have a second monitor, you
can capture it, for example. This
may be convenient for some
designers. You have
some information on one monitor, maybe a
browser, personal correspondence there. But on
this monitor, only some kind of movement is already
underway, some kind of creativity, and you want
only that, that is. Choose any
monitor according to  By default, the
main one you have will be selected and whether
to capture the cursor or not is up to
you to decide whether you need to
indicate something specifically with an arrow in the picture,
show what to do so that it is
visible what you are doing. And you
don’t need to know anything else, click
Okay, the basis of the content. We have in this
case. We imagine that we will
show our work in OBS. I hope
you are not confused by this recursion, but at
least most of you will need to
add a webcam. Our webcam
is in the video capture devices category.
Click the plus sign. Call the
video capture device whatever you like. In
this case, it’s a camera. Click Okay
and it opens. Well, the only camera
that is currently in the system
is a Logitech c920. I have it and it’s very important
that most beginners don’t do it. You
need to specify the value here.
Non-standard device values. And
custom ones, as you can see, are
almost square. I currently have
an image. Although the webcam produces
an image in a resolution of 1920 by 1080.
This should be 16 by 9 in the same
format as this one.  My screen with
OBS is full screen. Therefore, in any
case, you always select custom and in
the resolution, specify the resolution
that you most likely have. Marketers
placed it on the webcam box. The
maximum resolution that is possible
at the moment is 1920. 1080 is the maximum supported by the camera. This is
exactly what you
choose. If you selected everything correctly,
this is the resolution supported.
The picture will already be full-size. The
quality will be maximum. Believe me, a
huge number of people do not do
this and do not understand why
they have such terrible quality. Some kind of
cropped image. If you
stretch it to full screen, it is
some kind of blurry image, but no. The camera
can produce quite good quality.
It is simply at the standard values ​​​​of the
device.
Well, it will look like some kind of crap. You see,
what kind of blurry image if I stretch it. If
I need to, I will fill all this in. I
want a scene like this. There. Hello, I am
filming a course today, we will do
macrame and so on. Well, what kind of blurry image is this? Yes,
now, or should I change it to custom? Well, yes,
now it is stretched back immediately.
By the way, here is a trick for solving this problem:
right-click on the source that
you accidentally put there somehow.  changed
the size, lost it, moved it somewhere beyond
the screen boundaries, right-click to
convert and reset the conversion,
now the quality is indistinguishable from the
soap that was, I think you understand. The
only thing you will most likely need to
do is go back to the
sources. You can just double-click
on it to go to the parameters and
also if something is on the screen capture if you
need to change the monitor. Yes, everything with two
clicks. Go to any source in
its parameters. Well, either click this gear,
properties, highlight the desired item,
click properties with a webcam. Most likely,
you will need to play with
the colors a little because. Well, for example, on
this camera, the one on the left, damn. In short, I'm
confused. I seem to have a normal
human complexion. But here, there is some kind of drowned
man,
yellowish, some kind of strange.
Click on the video settings and most likely you will
need to uncheck the white balance if anything
and somehow tweak it, either
cooler colors as you like
or warmer some colors to
be more somehow filled with life.
You may also have to touch
shutter speed if you have automatic here is checked
then you need to uncheck it and
change
on some webcams these settings
will most likely not be available on cheap ones
But what can you do then it means you will have to deal with well,
without settings,
as the camera shows, so it will
show and now the most important thing will happen
magic because any
source that we added here in the
list we can scale like this using these
red lines, or rather the squares in the corners
We can even
rotate it using this circle If
suddenly necessary Well, Well, I'm an artist I
see it like this, this is cool I think it's
amazing We'll do it differently, but like this so that the
corners are not visible about everything A
brilliant artistic solution is simply
gods By the way, if you did crap, you
can use Control Z
to cancel everything under action in the same way and also a very
important trick that for some reason
people don't understand I was asked And how did
you make such a narrow camera there
maybe you turned the camera or
something, a webcam or something guys any
source can be cropped As you
like by pressing the ALT button on the keyboard
and using the same
crop it as you need
and you can do this with any source. That
is, if we take a screen capture and, for example,
don't want to show the right part there,
we don't need these buttons, we can
crop it all and arrange it
as you like. Accordingly, you can
see along this line that the green dotted line is cropped here. This is
very convenient and you
can do this with all the pictures.
Let's say I only need to
show me specifically now so that I don't really
cover anything from the interface.
And that's how I do it, and how I'm
actually recording now, roughly speaking, that's how it happens. That's how I did it and that's it.
My
scene is
some kind of tutorial on OBEES, roughly
speaking, now. You most likely don't
understand how I'm recording this, but
believe me, you don't need to know this now,
otherwise your head will explode. Well, then,
when you've done it again, you'll most likely
want to Add something else here, that
is, look, it could be text, you
can also name it. Enter
any text here, fonts, select
font size, choose anything,
make it small too, I chose 48, I want, let's say, here it is,
text, let's say, here
it will be with me. You can Add here
any image any image with a
transparent background a regular image it
doesn't matter click the image Okay
somehow call the review and select the file
you need let's say this is the wallpaper
on Here it is a little bit not the size of my
screen So I can somehow
change it move it as I specifically
want I want some more I want
some more pictures
for example I have prepared this
image with a transparent background it's like
me if anything in such a cartoon style you
can also twist and turn it all if
suddenly I don't need it I can crop it all
and so you can do it with any
source I repeat for some reason for
many this was not obvious If you
immediately understand this and
realize your capabilities then it will be
I think useful to you it looks kind of cool
we added a beautiful picture like this
on full screen but we blocked everything
that was before everything that we added
our webcam program interface where to
get it now the thing is that this
list of sources literally
needs to be perceived as a sandwich what is
on top will accordingly be in the
foreground if suddenly something  The
full screen size will be
higher than our camera and screen capture, then
accordingly it will cover everything. Therefore,
we simply take our image with the mouse
and enter it below
between the camera and the screen capture. Here is
the camera, our target has appeared. Perhaps we
need this image too, somewhere
below. We will do it like this.
Now we are covering the letters, these ones,
let's do what we typed under
the letters about or else. Use the arrows,
by the way, if you don't understand, it's not
particularly visible there. Use the arrows to
move a specific source by layers, that
is, hop, here it is now behind the letters, now in
front of the letters. This is very important to understand,
especially when your scene grows,
you will have many sources. Many people
in the future will most likely encounter the
problem that they cannot see something. They do
n't understand. Why something doesn't work?
First of all, this is connected with averts.
We will talk about this a little later. This is a
notification of some events on the stream.
Perhaps a Donation, perhaps a subscription, and so
on.
And people don't understand. Why it doesn't work?
Because most likely they
had a subscription in layers, for example, under
gameplay, under a picture of a program, or
maybe under a camera, under some
other  Get used to the image right away that these are
layers like in Photoshop, like
some kind of cake, it doesn't matter, get used to it, you understand
what's happening. The very bottom
screen capture then comes the image. This is with
the moon, then comes the camera, accordingly,
if you need to see the screen capture, then we
either hide the image so that it doesn't
exist. With this eye, we can hide
any source and then the
program interface appears. Or we push the image
below. Well, then it's not visible, there's no point in
it, but to understand the essence of these
sources. A completely normal example,
and then I recommend that you already study for
yourself what can be added here. For example, a
slide show so that you can add
several images, you indicate there
in milliseconds how long they will
change. Here is the time between slides, 800, and
here you throw the files either
directly into the folder or separately, files or a
folder, and here you will have, instead of one
image, changing after a certain
number of milliseconds, pictures. You
can also add a source. Media. This is
literally an opportunity to  Add
a video clip and also any manipulations with it
that we did with the camera
from the picture, there is more, less, and so on.
All this can be done with a video clip.
Add it from your hard drive
immediately, it will not appear, you need to press OK and
here it appears. This is my clip of me
running here in the game, playing, threw a canister and hit it, hit it
from the hard drive, bam,
beauty, in my opinion, let's say I need this for
broadcasts, but I need it like this somehow.
That's all the file stopped, by the way, again.
Go into it, click the
repeat checkbox and also read these
checkboxes here, restart playback
when there is a source becomes active.
If suddenly, for example, I need to hide
this source and then show it at the right
moment. I want it to restart from the
very beginning when it becomes
active, active, meaning
when it becomes visible, I click and it
will play from the very beginning, I
can do anything with it again, like this, let's say
Oh, I
accidentally touched the background wallpaper, by the way, you can lock them with
a lock if anything, like this and that's it,
you can't move them.  more so
as not to accidentally move something, I
'll do the same with these videos
instead of the camera, at least I'll put it
here like this, I'll crop it however I like, everything is
beautiful, op-op, that's perfect, it's
repeated over there. I have all this
image, this part of my content,
also in the corner, I want it like this, everything is
amazing in my opinion. Although, okay, let
it at least not be my face, but what's
happening in the center, so that it's somehow
clear with the source. I think we figured it out.
Now you need to understand what
scenes are. The thing is that
you may
need to constantly change this arrangement of elements in the broadcast,
there's a full-screen webcam
and so on, you don't always need to op-op, hold down
Alt, stretch it all,
by the way. Guys, let's talk about full
screen, we'll make a scene like this.
Let's talk about something.
blah-blah-blah-blah. This is naturally stupid, it
looks unprofessional, and it's uncomfortable for you.
From a production point of view,
how does it look from a
professional point of view? Well, and it's
just inconvenient from a time point of view,
it's just stupid, accordingly,
you leave everything.  How it was Well, if you
need it, naturally, you are there in the right
size, you can do it all already, you just
add a new scene with a plus
here, in the scenes, just like
you added new sources, scene 2,
a conversation with a chat, for example, there, or a full
webcam screen, it doesn’t matter. It’s not that important. This is also
for you, bam, here you have the Second Scene again,
we see this damned
Malevich Square, a rectangle, more precisely, and
here now it’s very important if you suddenly got
distracted, then now Come back and
look if you want to add to a
new scene in a different location. But the
same sources that you have in the
previous scene. You can switch
between them, then when you add a
source here, for example, a video capture device,
to add a camera type,
Add, don’t create a new one,
choose here, but Add an existing one
because, for example, the same Webcam cannot be
in two guises, so to speak, be in the
OS. It always works as one
source and you simply cannot add
if you add a new one, then a webcam. Well, the
standard one will not be shown in this, use
anything in. Specify that you will
not have a picture here, you will What is it?
Why don’t I have  It works well, you
probably need to disable the webcam. I don't
know, it's just not clear. For example,
it doesn't work with the webcam.
You add an existing video device
and select a camera.
Here will be a list of existing
sources of this type. Select a camera and
everything appears here, that is, on this
scene, all these manipulations with the red
borders. You can do it differently, that
is, here it will be like this, for
example, on full screen. Here is also
your image, for example, an
existing image, image number two. Oh, this is
my avatar,
I'll make it like this. I really
like it. It also
saves your resources and
it is very correct to do if
this source exists. You no longer need to
add it again. Image of course, you
can add a new one. The same one. Yes, but
better. Use existing images
and then design them as you want. And
now I have a scene like this. Let's
say I still need my
Media source, an existing video clip there, my
amazing Media source. I move it like this so that
my cameras are not visible so as
not to duplicate them,
and with the arrows I'll throw it to the very bottom like this, so that there it is in
the background, like this,
everything is smoother, look, the movement is
just creativity going. Let's say
we are talking like this.  Chat Hello, we
are starting the Stream, but when we move to
another scene, you
switch here with
the mouse or button, this is all in the settings.
If anything is done, go to the
hotkey settings. You are here,
unscrew the scene,
it will be called as it is called
here, that is, the scene, go to the scene,
let there be one on the numpad, and on scene 2,
scene two, conversations with chat, go to
scene 2, apply everything. Okay. Now we
can use buttons 1 and 2 to go at these
prices, everything.
And at the moment, our standard
fade-out is 300 milliseconds, here are the transitions
between scenes. Here you choose exactly what will be
between these scenes
when you move on. The
standard animation is, in principle, quite sufficient.
It will either fade-out, when it will
smoothly transition, op-op, one or two, I press. Yeah, I set
the duration, set it
longer and it all became a little
long. If some nuances
seem obvious to you, then believe me, I’m not just
focusing on them for no reason,
because I’ve encountered them many times in
my Path while I’m running this channel. While I’m
practicing myself, I  They ask something, that's the
problem when people really didn't
understand. How did you do it? From a
camera like this, like this, there's a tick like this. Only something
like this is what you flipped or
something else. It's funny because it can be
done. Like this, Alt was pressed, and so
you have free rein where to
place what, how to arrange it all.
In this corner, not in this corner, maybe. You, on the contrary, like a
camera like this so that it can be
seen that you have some kind of
shelf with a disk there in the background or
something else. It's all up to you.
If you click start recording, you'll
start recording everything that's happening
here on the screen. At the moment,
you've switched to a scene and it's being recorded. If you've switched to
another scene and it's being recorded, then maybe
you need another scene. Add here,
you'll add some other
screen capture. Here you'll show the same
ABS. And here you have this
amazing wallpaper. Here you're
inspired and looking at some
moon reflected in some kind of
icy lake in the mountains. It's amazing, just
inspiration is overflowing, perfect.
Here you have some kind of movement, some kind of
nonsense.  In general, what's actually
happening here, I threw it in. Well, okay. And
here we have professionalism, there's not even a camera,
though. Why is there no camera? We add a
device for photos, videos, existing
cameras, bam bam, but now we need to
do this. In this corner, so we look as
if at a wall.
That's it, it's very cool, everything is amazing.
To understand where our
creativity will be located if we
record it, we go to the settings, output, and
here is the recording item and the path to the recordings,
User, with the video bitrate, that is,
all my recordings will be in this folder.
Make sure you have enough space there
because this is currently drive C,
perhaps it's a system drive, maybe you
need to change the location. As for the
broadcast, here, accordingly,
connect to the service where you
stream. I stream on Twitch
[music].
Thank you very much, Twitch, for distracting
me from recording a video. I'm very
interested in this. Authentication is
two-factor authentication. Sometimes it annoys me, but it's
safe. I logged in to Twitch, but
in your case, it can be any
service that is listed here. But even if
you don't find it here, you can click on
customizable and enter the stream key
that  You will be provided with a site, I
said this already at the beginning of the video, in my case
it's Twitch, I press Okay, if I start
the broadcast with this button,
the broadcast will go on the site. In response, I
will change the name of the broadcast, some
game, or I will create a broadcast on YouTube,
this is already configured there, as for
OBS, here are quite
more savvy guys will say, but what about the
settings? After all, everyone should have
different ones, there are different settings for YouTube, for Twitch, and so on and so
forth. If you are a
beginner, this will only scare you, it will
only create unnecessary complications, you
will think that all this needs to be
understood, you need to set it up not just as simple, but as
advanced, there are more settings here for
audio recording, and so on. All this
needs to be changed, all this needs to be known. If you
want to know this, then I have a
detailed video on OBS settings, also
quite fresh, filmed several months ago.
If you want to understand in depth,
then Welcome to
the pop-up or the link in the description, I
will leave everything there in the pinned
comment or in the description under the video, and it is also
worth watching. In addition to this
video, if you want to develop, you want
more  To understand these settings in depth, you
also need to watch another video about
lags, streaming problems, and so on.
Even if nothing has
happened to you yet, nothing lags,
disappears, freezes, the broadcast does not drop,
and so on, it does not end. Even if
you didn't want it anyway. Watch
these tips. They will help you avoid
problems in advance. You will know
how to behave correctly in OBS and how to deal with
what problems. What to look for to avoid
confusion, so as not to feel
helpless. These two videos are really yours. They
played like a Saint. If you were seriously going to
study these two
videos and calmly rid yourself of 90% of the
problems, create something, start doing,
broadcasting, recording, filming,
whatever. Good luck. Well, master OBS. We haven't
finished yet. We haven't talked about
sound at all. And many say that sound is even more
important than the picture, which we have so
carefully configured here. Here we have
some kind of incredible artistic
ecstasy. Sound mixer. This is exactly the area
that should now capture our attention.
You are most likely confused by this
twitching sound from the
source.  Media, that is, from our
video that for some reason we can't
hear. Therefore, for now we will delete it
because more on this later. This
track remained from the camera, namely from
our branch that we added. Most likely,
you will not use the sound from it,
so we mute it
by pressing these three buttons and hide
so that it simply does not confuse us and
little by little we will now add the sounds
that we need. You can add sounds in
two different ways. You can add
them through scenes because this is this:
capturing the input audio stream, these are
microphones; capturing the output audio stream,
these are sounds. A computer is used to
add all the sounds on the computer
that you hear and play a clip
on YouTube, music in some player, etc., etc.,
etc. You
will hear all this here. But I recommend that you
go to the settings either with this button or
here with the button, go to audio, and here there
are global audio devices. That is,
all the audio devices that you
specify here globally will work on all scenes
if you understand that on all
scenes you need, for example, a microphone at
least.  Yes, the sound of the game, that is, the sound of the game, the
sound of the computer, it's all the same, then it's
better to add it here. Because it's
very unlikely that you will not
need to use it in some scene, but although
someone may need to make a
stub scene where you cannot be heard, and so on, and so on, and so
on, but this
can be implemented in different ways. Now I'll
show you the sound of the desktop - this is
just the computer sounds of the game, everything on the
computer will sound exactly with this
desktop sound. Here you select
your device, this will be the device
to understand where. Which one to choose, you most likely
may have several
items here. Select what
your headphones or your speakers are connected to
if they are not connected to the back of the
motherboard simply via a 3.5
cable, then This will most likely be
something like Realtek, and so on, and so
on. If you are connected to some USB
microphone, most likely
the name of your USB microphone will be here with
listening to some
third-party audio card, and so on. Here you select
this device, then the microphones, here you
can select up to four of them. You
select your microphone, it can be a
VIP camera microphone, which I do not
recommend using again. Yes, but
if  There is no other, then you can start with
this. Or you select this, this is
my microphone that
you are currently hearing. It’s just that another computer is
transmitting. In this system, it also exists. I
select it, press Okay,
two tracks appear. Here is the microphone, the
desktop sound has already been working, time and time again, and
accordingly, it’s empty, nothing
happens. Nothing is jumping here, there is no sound,
but if I turn on some
music on the neighboring monitor,
you see that everything is jumping
and now again. If you suddenly get distracted, you
need to understand how, with a sandwich of
sources, one topic is that what is
jumping here is what the broadcast hears, it is
not a copy of what you hear. You, because
you can do the same. Turn on the sound,
we hear it at a certain volume,
then it plays normally in the background,
but for the viewers, we can
turn it down
completely, it’s somewhere there, already beyond
this sensor, but
that is, regardless of what we hear,
we can increase or
decrease the volume for the viewers, and they hear. Not the
same. Especially considering that the Microphone
most likely needs to be adjusted here in the OS
so that its volume is in the
correct ratio with  some
background music with a game and so on.
Now I'll show you a very basic
setting that you can
copy to just get started. In this
case, I have pretty good volume levels.
If your microphone, when talking,
jumps somewhere around yellow like this, then you
can leave it like this.
The only thing you need to do is
press these three buttons opposite the microphone,
three dots, press the
filters, press the noise reduction plus sign. Okay, this
may already be called But it doesn't matter. Use
this one, then
add a limiter.
Okay, and set the value to -1 just so that if anything, there is
no overload. This is a
technical thing. If you don't understand
what's happening, forget about it in case.
If your microphone volume is initially
such that it is in the yellow zone
during a conversation and everything is fine,
but if suddenly this is for some
reason. Well, let's say we'll
emulate it like this. I, of course, removed this with the
slider here. But let's say your
microphone is so quiet here it's not
loud enough, then you have filters even before
you added  liter or Just
then the order again this
sandwich order Change add
here probably still gain so that you do
not screw up with compression because you
can do such a miracle there If you do not
understand what you are talking about in some
videos I saw where people
add a compressor ratio of 10 to one and
such why are you then writing this video damn
and this is during consultations
I very often had it It seems there is
some video where there is a guy
who adds a compressor and this
10 to one leaves such a well
amazing guy do you at least know
what a ratio is well okay
apparently such a video exists somewhere
add gain put it before
the limit that is noise reduction gain
Go here and twist plus until we have
the volume as I said but
by the way this is wrong now now I am
hammering here in the limiter because
I reduced here I add here in
overdrive In short, you understand the essence of what is
happening that you jumped here
but as I do not need to do that is you do
not need  adjust the volume here
if you don't have 100 here, that is, I
turn off the gain. And so I do it this way, that is, you use
this slider to achieve it
like I have here, technically
I did it because it's the wrong thing
just to show what you need to achieve so that
you have sound somewhere here,
respectively, the sound of the computer, the sound of
some game sounds, main
shots, possibly dialogues, and so on,
should be approximately at the same level with you, that
is, in the region of -20, maybe a little,
maybe lower, yes, you should check this at
least once to
see, or the obs will not be on your other
screen, and you will see
what volume levels are currently
sounding at the moment. Or you just
record how you play the game by ear during tests and
you will understand. Do you need to make the game quieter? Do you
need to make the game louder, and so
on, the music, most likely, you need to
make it a little quieter. If If we are talking
about background music
[music], then
you configure it to be comfortable for you
and for streaming it can also be quieter
[music].
Hello, I recommend. If you are here from -20
to  -10 then let the music be around
-40 somewhere around here no precision is
required approximately background
music should be here I
say this so that you understand right away at the beginning of
mastering the kit that here what is
shown is what the viewer hears and
not what you hear because you
may be on some headphones you can
make the microphone louder Maybe you have it
configured so that it is really very
quiet and you will drown in the volume of the music
that's how it will be
[music]
here already What kind of microphone did you have You
just have a drop in volume Although it seems like
nothing has changed you did not
start speaking more quietly you just need to
ensure that the volume level
is sufficient of course I understand that
this is a very basic sound setting Although
volume levels are relatively one
of the most important things that you simply did not have
this imbalance when
you cannot be heard the game is too loud and so on
and so on of course in
terms of processing here there is still an endless amount of
possibilities just like with the
BEES settings about which there is a
separate video on my channel about sound
I generally have  Of course, the course on
Boost is paid, but it is only needed for those who have already
tried everything, practiced,
mastered OBS and realized that they want
to understand sound a little better, how to
process sound from a microphone so that it is
pleasant for the viewer, in more detail, how
to use compression, how to use
equalization,
all the most important things about working
with sound are explained there in plain language. That is, essentially, without any
knowledge, you should come there and save
yourself the years that I spent
there at one time doing home
sound recording, some kind of streaming practice,
creating videos, and so on, and so on.
With my presentation, there is a
course there, it is a set of videos, these are not
four-hour lectures. If you want to
dive deeply into sound, or rather, not even
deeply, just very well
understand what is happening and somehow be
able to process sound for your
videos, your recordings, your courses,
and so on, then you can watch
the presentation of my course here on YouTube
or directly on Go to Boost, there I
have reviews. I periodically post
posts, there is a Telegram, where guys respond,
so far zero negative reviews.  I
actually had one negative experience, but
after 2 days the guy realized that it wasn't me that
was the problem. He also wrote that everything was
fine, so a good course helps a lot of
people, everyone is happy. I
suggest you do this if you need it, then go ahead,
but considering that most people
watch this video and you are newbies at the beginning,
try it this way, just broadcast it,
just understand. Do you like it? Are
you able to post videos? Do people watch it? And so on and so
forth, just
look at the results right away.  There's no need to waste
money here, buy the best
microphones there first. Try it
then watch the video about microphones on the
channel about settings. See if everything is
clear to you, study it quietly, and then
if you understand that you need it, then
Welcome there, my many years of
experience working with sound is one of my
strongest expertise, I
really have a dog there and can help
beginners quickly get into it without wasting
years on this what is important and what is not important, what
affects the result, what does not affect Well,
we are returning now we have scenes,
everything seems fine, there are sounds.
By the way, yes, since we added a
copper source to 10, I have it, too, you can
mute it,
since we added
sound sources to the global audio devices here,
they appear in each scene,
everything you don't need, we remove this tool.
If suddenly you added this
sound source and you want to hear it,
yes, firstly, you can adjust its volume
so that it is, for example,
somehow in the background or something else, but you
want to hear it, then you can do
this: go here, in the advanced
audio settings, these gears, you
see the line source here  Media and you do
not hear This is because you have
disabled listening That is, you
just click listening and output,
but here is a very tricky thing if you have
desktop sounds output as we
did, then you need to make only
listening and mute the output Why
What will happen When we click this,
this source, this line will begin
to be listened to on the device
that is indicated here is Audio and
where is the listening device Here it is
by default, most likely, this is the
same device that you selected
here is the desktop sound because
Well, you will no longer have several
headphones, most likely, one headphones or one
speaker is connected to one device,
you select it here most likely
It works
absolutely fine by default and here in the
advanced audio settings you
enable only listening
that's what happens now this is, I'll
make it quieter what happens this source
begins to be listened to On this
device, the desktop sound if we
make listening and output, that is,
this
track will also be output to Stream
like the others, they are only
listened to So it will be
output here and this track
will be output  and because we
are listening to it, it will sound and on the
desktop sound, it will be afraid,
you will have some kind of echo. And this also
happened very often, people did not understand.
Why do I have an echo, as if the
same thing sounds with a slight
delay. Avoid all this. That is, if
you want to hear, add
desktop sound and turn on only
listening, and then if you
set the volume to something, you can turn it down, or turn it up,
this is all you hear.
Both you and the broadcast. But if anything, you
can add microphones not in the
global device settings, but
add input audio stream capture.
Here, by the icon, you understand that this is a
microphone. Add a microphone, name
it somehow. And select
the device, too, a microphone. No, interestingly,
line, this one, everyone added me,
dad, this is also a microphone, you see, it is
duplicated, I have this global
microphone, this is what I added again. If
anything, avoid having
duplicate sources because this will be some kind of
strange, you will
not understand why you will hear twice, all
this with delays, this is all natural there,
according to sound theory, It can be excluded and
You will literally have a glitch in the sound, you
will not understand why it is
eaten up there, in short, it's difficult, forget it. Either
you always add everything in global
devices,
or you add the same microphone separately to each
scene. But then
you may get lost, I do not recommend
doing this and you will have filters. Well, on one
scene you have a filter, another is not here,
then in this case, don't get lost.
Add if anything if you added
some audio here. Here's a microphone.
Let's say we added this
microphone here again. If you add it to the
scene, then exactly the same principles as
other sources. If there is an existing
microphone, add the existing one. Add it,
specifically, capturing in ado Audio the
stream that we added to another
scene, then the filters will remain, that is, we
always don't forget about this. If there is
some source, we add to a new
scene that exists on another scene, it is
better to use it. So at the
moment, if you are only engaged in
recording, for example, a walkthrough is simply
recorded on your computer, maybe you are
recording some courses, and it shows
what you are doing on the screen, anything.
In general, you are filming there from the branch, perhaps
How do you sculpt pottery there and
Comment on this, yes, record it, then
edit anything, you already have
enough skills for recording. But if you are a Streamer, then in
order for the gentleman's set of a
beginner, so to speak, to be completed, we also
need to set up notifications about donations,
that is, about monetary donations and about
some subscriptions to our channels on
Twitch, YouTube, and so on. So, first of all,
don't be afraid that something has
changed. I'm recording on another day
because I didn't like how I dragged it out there.
Although the video is so long, but you need to
figure it out. You, beginners, deserve to be
told in detail about everything that
concerns alerts, namely,
notifications about subscriptions, and so
on. I recommend using the
streams service. The interface of this site, in my
opinion, is very intuitive at times. If you
go to the main page, it will be difficult for you
to get where you need to go, even if you
know where you need to go. But think of
this as an investment in the future. Because
if you figure this out and
start hosting your alts here, then in
the future, a lot of cool things will happen. This is
exactly where my neat one is.
The widget under the webcam where
subscribers change. Subs are there. Whoever gave a subscription also
donated very neatly and beautifully. This is
done on this site with a custom
widget. It's difficult for now, we'll
only get through the basic level now. But if
you do all this here, it will be
easy for you to get into it later using
some guides from YouTube, maybe in
English if you speak
English. In general, let's not be
cunning, login, click connect, and use the
social network on which you will
stream. Is it Twitch or YouTube? I'll
log in to Twitch. But it doesn't matter. In
fact, we get to a panel with various
statistics: who subscribed, there are some
even by date, all sorts of subscriptions, donations, and so on
and so forth. I recommend immediately
saving this specific page
in your bookmarks so that you can go here right away
and not to the main page. Believe me, I'll
save you a billion nerves. We are
interested in broadcasting tools here, and
then I have an overlay here. A bunch of overlays, you wo
n't have this. Don't be
afraid, these are my tests there, and so on,
I have them for different games.  I do some
experts with different colors and so on.
This is a more advanced thing for now,
you don't need to click new overlay.
Select the resolution, there, remember the
canvas. Yes, here you have the resolution of your
canvas, your black
rectangle of Malevich, here you select
this resolution, most likely,
it will be 1080. Start here, instead of the
Malevich rectangle, here is a
rectangle marked with dots, this is,
roughly speaking, your screen. What do you do? You
click the plus sign here. Well, either this is a widget,
add a widget. Don't be afraid of English,
guys, you're learning nothing, everything is
fine.
Plus box, then you place it. Where do
you want it to be on the screen?
Well, most likely, something like this, don't
worry too much about this,
and in fact, in fact, you can
finish here. This is especially for beginners. This
Muley button allows you
to emulate events on a stream, for example,
Follow on Twitch. Yes, this is a subscription, that's what it's
called. Click the button, and it will appear now.
There is already some kind of beautiful animation,
of course, you can customize everything, fonts,
colors, and so on. Picture. What
will pop up for you? But if you  If you don't want to
yet, you can leave it alone.
But if you click on this
alertbox that we added, and here there
is a list of events that will be
shown here, and for each event, there
will be a gear where you
can configure all of this. That is, if
here we look at the name, this is the name of the
person who subscribed and knew Fallon,
this is in English, he
subscribed to the channel. Yes, that's what we did,
now she's doing this. That's how we did it, we
also emulate here,
here's a mini subscribed to the channel, I'm there, what
6000? Did I change it or something. In general, you get the idea. You
can play around here. If you suddenly
log in with YouTube, then you
will have a slightly different list here. That is,
you only have the usual soup scriber there, you
have a super chat there. There are even,
if anything, purchases through YouTube, there
are some of these subscription services,
sponsors, and so on, all of this can be
configured there. If you log in with another
account, that is, YouTube, what do we
do next? Next, we click on this
copy button, the overlay URL, that is,
we copy  link and go to BS in all we
add a new source, this will already be in
our browser, we add it, call it something like
Alberta blah-blah-blah
notification - This is if anything in Russian
here in the URL address we click
paste and just the link
that was copied width we make
the resolution more precisely 1920 by 1.0080
Well, this is how we did it, yes, we noticed the canvas size
Yes, I just pressed one two
My scenes changed because
we set up hot keys everything
else, don't touch it, set it like this
Okay We have a new source, it's
transparent It's empty, but if
someone subscribes to us, some
other event will happen on the stream, which is
marked with checkboxes there, then it will be
displayed here By the way, I forgot to say that
firstly, you can rename it, it
will be alts Yes, you need to click safe here
for it all to start working and if you
make any changes here on the
site so that they start working for you in
You need to save this overlay, the
alerts work where we
placed them on the stremelements website, everything is
fine. If you want to change
fonts, colors, and so on, this will
help you with any animations, gifs, you can
upload them there. The interface is
not difficult to figure out, but if you suddenly find it difficult, then
just don’t change anything. It’s a pretty
nice design, and so on, and now I
think you understand. Why I once
emphasized this
sandwich principle of sources because
alerts are essentially. Well, this is an empty
square. Yes, this is an empty rectangle. You
can easily take it by accident and
leave it there for
measurement. You seem to have them behind all sources.
And if suddenly someone subscribes to you,
nothing appears. It is
actually there, there is a subscription to the channel, but
the pictures before it are a picture. You understand, and
you should keep in mind which
sources should be at the top,
especially if you add something new in the future
and forget the old sources.
Because with each new source, if we
add some image, it doesn’t matter,
even if it’s empty, it always remains at the top,
so don’t get lost here. If
anything happens later, order  Change layers so that everything
is shown to you. As
for receiving donations, how did you plan?
When someone
sends you money, there is
no obvious choice here because in some
strange services, the withdrawal does not
work, somewhere something is blocked. There is
donationallert. There is Donat P. There is
donate. There is trimelement, which has its own
payment system. Most likely, it
will work well outside of Russia, but it can also
work with this one, which
works fine with Russia. That is, there are
many options. I will tell you the essence. How it
works, what you need to understand. I will show
everything using the example of donationallerts. Again, the most
basic setting, if anything,
change some fonts so that the colors are
colored, and so on. That's all.
Later, here we go to the
notification widgets section. Most likely,
you also have a group with a default variation at the beginning.
We just take the link for
embedding. We don't show the copied one here to anyone.
I won't show it either. I just
copy the icon from it. BS. We also add
another browser, this will already be donations
here. You can  leave the width height also
insert this link here OK this
source is no longer fullscreen we can
move it right in we can as we want in
fact non-fullscreen sources
can also create a stream limit Just
there as I explained to you how it was easier
put it somewhere here and on the site
you can launch a test notification
it is done like this this orange
variation by default this is just donations the
most donated on the lecture of this site
click on this gear
make a test notification
[music]
message Here is such an alert if
someone sends you 475 rubles and some
message It will also be read everything is
amazing Everything is great But where do you
send this Donation where actually to
pay where to put money
on all similar services this is called the
donation page That is, this is the same
page Here is the main link where a
person goes and there will be a beautiful
form to support you there to enter the
amount enter the message and so on Everything
will happen on this page You can
also design something for the
fund there more precisely indicate the color of the buttons
and so on ...  So then
you place this link accordingly, also
copy this link here, you place it
under the stream in your description or there,
if this type, you can make a picture
that can be clicked on
and there you will be taken to this
donation page, a person will see something like this. That
is, he can literally call his moment a
sandwich, this is by the way, me. Under such a someone,
apparently, I donated to someone, we need to start
bitrade here there are some presets for amounts,
even as I understand it, I can enter any
amount myself, it would of course be nice if I could
throw someone a million
200, you send Here there are even
some voiceovers blah-blah, but for each
service, everything will be a little different here,
but it’s definitely not difficult, you’ll
figure it out. But what is this very
browser anyway? Essentially, you add a
browser page to your OBS, that is, the
same page on the Internet. You can,
instead of these donations, simply write
google.com here, bam, here it is Google, that is,
essentially it’s just a page, but we
naturally add our own page here, some
strange one with  Some strange
link just alert services
essentially provide you with a unique
page where they display
messages specifically about what's happening
on your stream. That is, this is essentially
just a browser page. In the
old days, we used to open it all in a
regular browser, capture it with a window, and
what I said at the beginning of the video, then we
removed the green background using the
chromakey filter, that's a completely different story, but
I want you to understand what kind of
source this is and why donations are
made through it. This is now conveniently
done. You set it up once and that's it.
No problems. Alerts will now appear forever.
Beauty. Real subscribed to the channel. Wonderful,
naturally. Some advanced
settings. They don't show you here for
beginners. This is simply not necessary. Perhaps in
future videos I'll tell you how to
make some advanced widgets in
Stream Elements. How it all works. And
you, knowing this basic information,
will navigate my channel perfectly. I
hope I've managed to
convey all the necessary information in an accessible form for beginners
to get started,
to take the first steps in this.  In
the world of streaming, in the world of OBS, if the video
was useful to you, don't forget
to like and promote the video
so that others will come across it and so that they can
start their
journey into this Brave New World with this video.
Write comments about what you
do, why you decided to
use OBS, who you are, what you do,
what specific action you
will control, in this
Malevich square, rectangles, what
will happen there. I
have a section in my Discord for streamers where you
can ask your questions. Again, a
disclaimer, like in other videos, no
one owes you anything. There is a separate
section for streamers. Read the rules
there. Regular guys give advice, just maybe
more experienced ones. You can ask. They
don't charge for asking. As they say,
come on in, be part of the community. This is not a
problem, of course, we don't like stupid people and lazy people
there, but don't be afraid, write and
ask. Believe me, there is a big
difference between a lazy person, a real
fool, and just a person who doesn't
understand something.
It's normal to ask, it's normal.
People just do it.  I've
already suffered some trauma from this over
the years of running this channel. So, these are the
disclaimers I
have to say. Well, especially for
you. If you're new and have come to this channel for the first time,
I'll make a separate playlist with
videos specifically about OBS, on various
little things, tricks, and so on. I have a lot of
useful videos, some old ones, but still
relevant and useful, just so you can
further develop in the possession of
this program. A separate playlist is
for streamers,
among other things, there are some chatty,
more philosophical ones about this area, about
how you need to keep your path there, and so
on. For those who like to listen to my chatter,
there are videos about streamers, but I'll make a
separate playlist, specifically
technical ones, please. I think this
will be useful for beginners, just along with this
video about OBS settings, more detailed ones
about lags, and so on. Everything will be there.
Therefore, watch it too if you want to
further educate yourself in this area. If
you're going to take this seriously,
thank you all for watching. Bye, everyone. And have a
good stream.